A Guide to the Virginia Secretary of Transportation: Correspondence and Subject Files, 1972-1983
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Office of the Secretary of transportation: Correspondence and Subject Files, 1972-1983
The Library of Virginia
32184
3 cu. ft. (3 boxes)
Need Info
Virginia. The Office of the Secretary of Transportation
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Accession 32184 was transferred by the Office of the Secretary of Transportation, 9th St. Office Building, Richmond, Va, on 23 August 1984.
Biographical Information
In 1970, the Governor's Management Commission Study recommended the creation of six "Deputy Governors" to assist the Chief Executive in his managerial duties. Compatible functions of government were grouped under these administrative heads, who would serve as the Governors top management team or "secretariats," as they are called now.
Governor Linwood Holton's top priority for the 1972 session of the General Assembly was a proposal for a Governor's Cabinet, reorganizing state agencies into six major departments--each headed by a secretary appointed by the governor. Transportation and public safety was one of these six departments. The office of Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety was created on April 8, 1972, by an act passed by the General Assembly. Governor Holton appointed Wayne A. Whitham, a member of the Winchester City Council, as the first Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety. When Whitham took office on July 1, 1972, he was responsible for State Highway Commission, Division of Motor Vehicles, Department of State Police, Highway Safety Division, Office of Emergency Services, Department of Military Affairs, Virginia State Crime Commission and the Law Enforcement Officers Training Standards Commission. The Office has undergone a series of administrative reorganizations since. On April 12, 1976, the Legislature established separate secretariats for transportation and for public safety, effective July 1, 1976. On July 1, 1984, the offices were again combined. Most recently, the Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety was divided into separate secretariats on February 22, 1990. The Secretary of Transportation is a member of the Governor's Cabinet, and is appointed by the governor, subject to confirmation by the General Assembly. The Secretary is responsible to the governor for the Department of Transportation, Department of Rail and Public Transportation, Department of Aviation, Department of Motor Vehicles, Virginia Port Authority and the Motor Vehicle Dealers Board.
Wayne A. Whitham, the first Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety, was reappointed by Governor-elect Miles E. Godwin, Jr., in December 1973 and by Governor-elect John N. Dalton in December 1977. Whitham suffered a heart attack in August 1978 and resigned in December 1978. On June 7, 1984, Whitham died in Richmond, Virginia. Governor Dalton named George M. Walters, a former top executive of the Reynolds Metals Corporation, to succeed Whitham as Secretary of Transportation. Walters served until the end of Dalton's term in January 1982. Governor-elect Charles S. Robb, the first Democrat to be elected governor since 1965, did not retain any of Dalton's cabinet secretaries. Robb appointed Andrew B. Fogarty, Dalton's assistant secretary for financial policy, as Secretary of Transportation. On July 1, 1984, the secretariats of transportation and public safety were combined again. As a result this partial reorganization of state government, Governor Robb appointed Fogarty Secretary of Administration and Franklin E. White, Secretary of Public Safety, assumed Fogarty's Transportation duties. White, who served as a White House liaison official under President Jimmy Carter, resigned in June 1985 to become the New York state commissioner of transportation. He was replaced by Andrew Fogarty who served until the end of the Robb administration. He later served as Governor Gerald L. Baliles chief of staff from August 1986 to October 1989 when he resigned to become a vice president with CSX Corporation.
In December 1985, Governor-elect Gerald L. Baliles, picked Vivian E. Watts, a northern Virginia legislator, as Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety. Watts served until the end of Baliles' term in 1990. In 1995 she was elected to her old seat in the Virginia House of Delegates. On February 22, 1990, the Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety was divided into separate secretariats. Governor L. Douglas Wilder, appointed John G. Milliken, a member of the Arlington County Board of Supervisors, as the Secretary of Transportation. Milliken resigned on December 17, 1993.
In February 1994 Governor George Allen, the first Republican elected governor since 1977, appointed Robert Martinez as Secretary of Transportation. Martinez was born in Cuba and had served as Deputy Administrator for the Marine Administration and Associate Deputy Secretary of Transportation during President George H.W. Bush's administration. At the end of Governor Allen's term in January 1998, Martinez joined the Norfolk Southern Corporation. Shirley Ybarra, deputy Secretary of Transportation in the Allen administration, was named Martinez's successor by Governor-elect James Gilmore. Ybarra previously worked as a special assistant to Transportation Secretary Elizabeth Dole during President Ronald Reagan's administration. Ybarra served until the end of Gilmore's administration in January 2002. Whittington W. Clement, a former lawyer and long-time member of the Virginia House of Delegates representing the City of Danville, was appointed Secretary of Transportation by Governor Mark R. Warner in 2002. Pierce R. Homer, Deputy Secretary of Transportation, replaced Clement in 2005.
Scope and Content
Contains files pertaining to Virginia transportation concerns, including but not limited to the Department of Motor Vehicles, Port Authority, and Military Affairs. This collection contains; Budget Reviews, Governor's Year End Reports, Legislation, Regulations, as well as, Correspondence and Subject files.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I. Correspondence and Subject Files, 1972-1983
Contents List
- Series I. Correspondence and Subject Files, 1972-1983., Extent: 3 cu. ft. (3 boxes). (Box 1-3)
  The original order of files has been maintained as they were recieved from the agency.
  - Virginia National Guard: A Special Report, 1972-1983. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Military Affairs, Department of: Veteran's Day, 1972-1983. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Military Affairs: Emergency Work Authorization, 1972-1983. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Military Affairs, Department of, 1972-1983. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Department of Motor Vehicles: Non-Resident Violator Compact, 1972-1983. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Department of Motor Vehicles: Branch Offices, 1972-1983. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Department of Motor Vehicles: State of License Issue and Revenue Collection, 1972-1983. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - National Association of State budget Offices, 1972-1983. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Governor Year End Report, 1977. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Motor Vehicles, Division of: Office Space, 1972-1983. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Governor's Year End Report, 1979. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Governor's Year End Report, 1980. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Governor's Year End Report, 1981. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Department of Motor Vehicles: Abandoned Vehicle Program (and Fund), 1972-1983. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Personnel: Compensation Program, 1980. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Governor's Year End Report, 1976. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Governor's Year End Report, 1972. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Planning District communications Meeting, 1980. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - miscellaneous, 1972-1983. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Interstate Highways I-95, 1972-1983. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Department of Motor Vehicles: Fuel Tax Collections, 1972-1983. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Brault, Adelard C., 1972-1983. (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Campbell, Archie, 1972-1983. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Virginia National Guard: A Special Report, 1972-1983. (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Cantrell, Orby L., 1972-1983. (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Giesen, A. R. (Pete), Jr., 1972-1983. (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Gray, Elmon T.: Senate, 1972-1983. (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Butler, M. Caldwell: U.S. House, 1972-1983. (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Jones, George W.: House, 1972-1983. (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Miller, Nathan H., 1972-1983. (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Byrd, Harry F., Jr., 1972-1983. (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Daniel, Robert W., Jr.: U.S. House, 1972-1983. (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Daniel, W. C. "Dan": U.S. House, 1972-1983. (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Parris, Stanford E.: U.S. House, 1972-1983. (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Wampler, William C.: U.S. House, 1972-1983. (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Whitehurst, G. William: U.S House, 1972-1983. (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Legislators Washington, 1972-1983. (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Lynchburg Municipal Airport, 1972-1983. (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Secretary of Transportation: Elva Hill - Invoices, 1982. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Secretary of Transportation: Elva Hill - Invoices, 1983. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Reciprocal Parking Agreement - Handicapped Drivers, 1972-1983. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Motor Vehicles, Division of, 1972-1983. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Federal Government Agencies: General File, 1972-1983. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Legislation: Secretary f Transportation, 1979-1981. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Parking: to archives, 1972-1983. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Federal Regulations Transportation, 1972-1983. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Virginia Port Authority: Maritime Administation Loan, 1972-1983. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Virginia Port Authority: Personnel - unemployment compensation, 1972-1983. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Virginia Port Authority: Labor, 1972-1983. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Virginia Ports and Port Authority: Study Commission, 1972-1983. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Virginia Port Authority, 1972-1983. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Virginia Alcohol Safety Action Program: 1 of 3, 1972-1983. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Virginia Alcohol Safety Action Program: 2 of 3, 1972-1983. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Virginia Port Authority: Personnel, 1972-1983. (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Transportation Secretary of,: Personnel - Employment and Position Report, 1972-1983. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Transportation Secretary of,: Telephone Services, 1972-1983. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Transportation Secretary of,: Supplies - Office, 1972-1983. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Personnel: Temporary Employees, 1972-1983. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Transportation Secretary of,: Subscription Memberships, 1972-1983. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Transportation Secretary of,: Services and Labor, 1972-1983. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Transportation Secretary of,: On-loan and surplus, 1972-1983. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Transportation Secretary of,: Personnel - Employment and Position Report, 1972-1983. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Transportation Secretary of,: Office Space, 1972-1983. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Transportation Secretary of,: Mission and Goals, 1972-1983. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Transportation Secretary of,: Property - Governor's Council on Transportation, 1972-1983. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Transportation Secretary of,: Invoices, 1972-1983. (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Transportation Secretary of,: Furniture - Office, 1972-1983. (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Transportation Secretary of,: Equipment - Office, 1972-1983. (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Secretary of Transportation: Zoller's Report Backup, 1972-1983. (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Transportation Secretary: Agency Heads Memo to, 1972-1983. (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Transportation Secretary of,: Disposition of Files, 1972-1983. (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Transportation Secretary of,: Micellaneous Correspondence, 1972-1983. (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Transportation Secretary of,: Administrative Functions, 1972-1983. (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Insurance: Secrtary of Transportation, 1972-1983. (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Transportation Secretary of,: Parking - State Employee, 1972-1983. (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Transportation Security of Building - 9th street, 1972-1983. (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Personnel: Secretary of Transportation - Procedures, 1972-1983. (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Personnel: Secretary of Transportation, 1972-1983. (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Transportation: Typeriters, Purchase and Rental, 1972-1983. (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Secretary of Transportation: Congratualtion Letters, 1972-1983. (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Virginia Military Institute: Conference, 1982. (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Secretary of Transportation: Conference - Aviation Commission, 1982. (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Transportation Secretary of,: Files, 1972-1983. (Box 3, Folder 29)